Finding Aid for D.C. Allen House of David Collection, 1795-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Publications
  - Publications of the House of David
    - Brief concordance to the Star of Bethlehem (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, [ 1910 ?] ) 158 p. (Box 1)
      ([Allen annotation: A few copies were printed up for the use of the colony officers and for the preachers. Printed in black and/or blue ink on cheap paper. Most of the copies were later bound up with the Star in the one volume edition.] (BHL has photocopy of cover only))
    - Brief pocket concordance to "Extracts" and "Private Word" ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, ca. 1905 ]) 36, 17 p., 2 copies (Box 1)
      ([Allen annotation: Contains "Extracts from John Wroe" and "Extracts from the 'Extracts.'"])
    - Brief points of Benjamin's travels (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David 1926 ) 30 p. Cover title: Very brief points of Benjamin's travels: which perhaps never were finished. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: 1st edition. The wraps are gray in color with red printing and, strangely, the text is not printed in blue ink.)
    - Brief points of Benjamin's travels (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, [ 1968 ]) 30 p. Cover title: Very brief points of Benjamin's travels: which perhaps never were finished., 2 copies (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: 2nd edition. Reissued with no change of date from the 1st edition. The type has been completely reset, the wraps are buff in color and the text is printed in blue ink.)
    - A brief scripture concordance (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, [circa 1906 ]) 90 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: completely without imprint. Intended for the use of the preachers.)
    - Chorus song book (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, [ca. 1920 ]) 73 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: the first 43 pages are a reprint of "Song book, words by Benjamin" followed by 11 blank leaves. This is followed by a title page for the Chorus song book and pages 45-73 plus 10 blank leaves. In the only copy which it has been possible to locate mimeographed slips with additional songs have been tipped onto the blank leaves. BHL has photocopy of cover only)
    - The comforter: the mother's book ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, ca. 1908 ]) 208 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: 1st edition. This was the first of Mary's "Comforters." The frontis portrait is of Mary. Many copies destroyed by the Dewhirst faction, at the time of the separation.)
    - The comforter: the mother's book. Book 2. 1st ed. (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1912 ) 144 p., 2 copies (Box 2)
    - Copy of a letter written by J. J. Jezreel August 30th, 1882 ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1905 ]) 7 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: The work is without imprint or any printing information to connect it with the House of David.)
    - Correspondence with W.J. Barnard and other matters of general interest to the members ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1928 ]) 35 p. (Box 2)
    - The dark and bright side of man and woman (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David 1931 ) 16 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: This originally appeared in "Dialogues 1 to 20" printed 1908. At the time of the separation and ill feeling between the rival colonies it was rediscovered and reissued as a none to subtle attack on Mary Purnell. The initial leaf bears "Copyright 1931 House of David, Benton Harbor, Mich." Distribution was probably intended more for members of the faith and those sympathetic to the colony than for the general public.)
    - Debate references, Earth and Sun ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, ca. 1905-1910 ) 6 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Only a few copies printed and not intended for general distribution, but for the use of the preachers. There is no imprint or printing information. The references are to the writings of John Wroe, James Jezreel, Benjamin and the scriptures.)
    - Dialogue between the angel Uriel and Esdras ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, ca. 1915 ]) 51 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Without imprint. Players script with instructions.)
    - Dialogue--Locating paradise ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, ca. 1908 ]) 27 p. (Box 2)
    - Dialogues 1 to 20 ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, ca. 1908 ]) 127 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: without imprint. The first printing of the dialogues used at the auditorium at the colony and sometimes by the traveling preachers. Selected dialogues were later printed up in the five Books of dialogues for distribution to the general public. This volume was for the use of the cast only.)
    - Dialogues 21 to 27 ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, ca. 1908 ]) p. 128-259 (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Paper labeled stiff wraps. The label calls for dialogues 21 to 27. This has been corrected in mss. to read 21 to 29 (as the volume contains). No imprint of any sort. Intended for members participating in the dialogues only. These dialogues are based mainly on the dissensions between Benjamin's followers and the 5th and 6th churches.)
    - Dialogues 21 to 29 ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, ca. 1908 ]) p. 128-257 (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Stiff wraps with title printed on wrap. Pages 128 through 223 correspond with "Dialogues 21 to 27," The balance from pages 224 has been revised and reset, reducing final page in this volume to 257. there are two dialogues numbered 27 thus this work actually contains dialogues 21-30.)
    - Dialogues 31 to 36 ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, ca. 1910 ]) p. 236-404 (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Without imprint. There is a hiatus in the pagination. This volume as a continuation, should begin with page 260. Portions of these dialogues were printed later as part of the Books of dialogues for public distribution however this volume was for the use of the cast and was not given general distribution among the membership.)
    - Dialogues 37 to 39 ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, ca. 1910 ]) 32 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: No imprint whatsoever. These dialogues were presented for the membership only and were not for the general public. These pamphlets were in the form of a script for the use of the participants in learning their lines.)
    - Dialogue 40 ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, ca. 1910 ]) 20 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: This dialogue sets forth the Israelite views on Christmas. Again this would appear to be a misnumbering as there is a dialogue 40 included in Dialogues 40 to 43.)
    - Dialogues 40 to 43 ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, ca. 1910 ]) 80 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Annotation identical to that for Dialogues 37 to 39.)
    - Dialogue 44 ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David 1916 ]) 48 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: The final number in the series of dialogues and one of the most elaborate having a cast of 73. As with the "Rule book" and the "Perjury books" this is in bright pink wrappers. Copies of the dialogue or play, as the wrapper indicates, were not to be distributed.)
    - [Dialogues: no collective title] ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, ca. 1906 ]) 16, 12, 22, 12, p. (Box 2)
      (includes "A controversy between Jew and Gentile and Israel," "A dialogue between Jew and Gentile and Israel," New Year dialogue," "A dialogue between Jew and Gentile and Israel.")
    - [Dialogues: no collective title] ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, ca. 1906 ]) [69], 8, 85 p. (Box 2)
      (includes "A dialogue and controversy between Jew, Gentile and Israel," "A dialogue and controversy between Jew, Gentile and Israel," "A controversy between the House of David and the two old houses")
    - Eden's paradisical liberty: prohibition(?) temperance(?). Book 1 (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, c 1916 ) 29 p. (Box 2)
      (BHL has photocopy only)
      (Allen annotation: Strangely enough Book 1 states on the title page "Copyright 1916." This would indicate Book 1 was issued after Book 2 (1915). This is probably explained by the fact that all or nearly all the material appeared first in "Scriptures are in favor of wet")
    - Eden's paradisical liberty: prohibition(?) temperance(?). Book 2 (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, c 1915 ) 33 p. (Box 2)
    - Elocution (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, ca. 1914 ) 8 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Completely without imprint information. Although innocent appearing this was for the purpose of speech training for those members who might be called to appear as court witnesses in the Fortney trial. Some use was later made of this by the preachers for self cultivation. As in the case of the "Rule book" and the "Perjury books" the wraps are bright pink.)
    - Extracts from Book no. 2 entitled Eden's paradisical liberty: prohibition(?) temperance(?): prove all things before voting! Folder no. 5. ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1916 ]) 4 p. (Box 2)
    - Extracts from the books of Esdras, Tobit, Wisdom of Solomon, Book of Enoch (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, ca. 1906 ?) 28 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Chapter and verse pertinent to the Israelite faith have been extracted from various apocryphal works. Only a few copies printed for limited distribution to the preachers and membership.)
    - A few brief facts concerning the House of David: its purpose, government, home life, industries; and also about joining the commonwealth (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, [ 1930 ]) 4 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Issued immediately following the separation but in use for only a few months.)
    - A fishing expedition ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1923 ]) 16 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Undoubtedly written by Judge Dewhirst)
    - The flaming ball of fire. (Box 2)
      (For volumes 1-3 see Rolling ball of fire)
    - The flaming ball of fire. Vol. 4 (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, c 1925 ) 112 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: 1st edition. The 1st issue is printed on cheap pulp paper. The frontis portrait is the same as in volume 3. There is no literature list. The 2nd issue is on coated paper stock with the exception of the title page which appears to be a utilization of an overrun from the 1st issue. The frontis portrait is the same as the 1st issue and there is no literature list.)
      - 1st issue, 2 copies (Box 2)
      - 2nd issue, 3 copies (Box 2)
    - The flaming ball of fire. Vol. 5 (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, c 1925 ) 112 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: 1st edition. The 1st issue is printed on cheap pulp paper. The frontis portrait is the same as in volume 3. There is no literature list. The second issue is printed on coated paper stock.)
      - 1st issue, 2 copies (Box 2)
      - 2nd issue, 3 copies (Box 2)
    - The flaming ball of fire. Vol. 6 (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, c 1925 ) 110 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: 1st edition. 1st printing on cheap pulp paper. In addition to the regular frontis portrait of Benjamin there is a second frontis portrait of Benjamin seated on a white horse. A 2nd printing is on coated stock. There is no literature list. Portrait as in volume 3 and an additional one of Benjamin seated on a white horse.)
      - 1st issue, 2 copies (Box 2)
      - 2nd issue, 3 copies (Box 2)
    - Fun in a vaudeville agency ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, ca. 1915 ]) 16 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Without imprint. Script for the use of the actors in this comedy presented at the colony park. Strictly for amusement with no religious undertones.)
    - Garden of Eden dialogue ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, ca. 1908 ]) 25 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Without imprint. A dialogue version of material that was later to be printed as "Where did Cain get his wife." Copies were printed up for use of the cast in presenting the play at the colony's auditorium but were not given general distribution among the membership.)
    - The House of David: its purpose, government, home life, industries, vocations and requirements for membership (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, ca. 1940 ) 24 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Although undated internal evidences indicate a printing after 1937. Said to have been written by Judge Dewhirst.)
    - [House of David song book] ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, ca. 1932 ]) 33 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Without imprint or title, a preliminary issue, on poor paper, of the revised song book for the membership, typographical variation on page 22 and without index.)
    - House of David song book ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, ca. 1932 ]) 33 p., 2 copies blue and white (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Copies are bound in both blue and white wraps.)
    - [Hymns] ([Benton Harbor, Mich. Israelite House of David, ca. 1908-1910 ]) 136 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Without title page or imprint. This greatly expanded hymnal replaced the small "Songs of the House of David" issued ca. 1905. contains 138 hymns.)
    - I inquired of one of the angels concerning this Son of Man; who he was; whence he was; and why he accompanied the Ancient of Days ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, ca. 1905 ]) 7 p (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Printed on singleton leaves and then cemented at the inner margins into pamphlet form.)
    - The ingathering of Israel (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, [19--]) 4 p. (Box 2)
    - The ingathering of the children of Israel (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, 19--) 32 p. (Box 2)
    - Instruction book and chart for tempering and hardening steel: based upon scientific laws note heretofore understood, yet always existing (Benton Harbor, Mich.: G. Wheeler & Co., [ 19-- ]) 9 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: George Wheeler was one of Benjamin's early converts. This work was apparently printed up under the G. Wheeler & Co. imprint with a view that it would have an easier technical acceptance than had it borne the Israelite House of David imprint.)
    - The invitation from the House of David ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1905 ]) 22 p. (Box 2)
    - Israel's work both natural and spiritual ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 19--] ) 2 p. (Box 2)
    - John Wroe reference book (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, ca. 1905 ) 61 p., 2 copies (Box 2)
    - Joseph in Egypt: Joseph sold into Egypt, and deliverance of Jacob's family: descriptive dialogue in seven acts (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1913 ) 60 p. (Box 2)
    - The key of the House of David (Benton Harbor, Mich: House of David 1911- ) 32 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen identifies four printings but without sufficient description to match BHL holdings. Allen printings:
      1st edition, printed during the winter of 1910-1911
      2nd edition, 1917 with the flag and eagle cut on the upper wrap
      3rd edition, ca. 1928 flag and eagle within single rule border
      ca. 1930s there are two issues of this edition, differing only in that one has the wrapper title within a single heavy rule border and the other has the title within a double, thin, thick border.
      The BHL holdings are grouped into six sets based on physical characteristics.)
      - Set 1. Allen 2nd ed., publisher "Israelite House of David, Benton Harbor", Grayish tan wraps, chain border, flag and eagle printed in two colors (Box 2)
      - Set 2. Allen 3rd ed., publisher "Israelite House of David, Benton Harbor" portrait of Benjamin without hat, Green wraps, thick border, flag and eagle printed in one color (Box 2)
      - Set 3. publisher "House of David, Drawer G, Benton Harbor" portrait of Benjamin with hat, 3 copies Green wraps, thick border, flag and eagle printed in one color (Box 2)
      - Set 4. Allen 1930s ed., publisher "House of David, P.O. Box 477, Benton Harbor", Light green wraps, thin, thick border, flag and eagle printed in one color (Box 2)
      - Set 5. Allen 1930s ed., publisher "House of David, P.O. Box 477, Benton Harbor", 4 copies Light green wraps, thick border, flag and eagle printed in one color (Box 2)
      - Set 6. publisher "House of David, P.O Box 1067 Benton Harbor" portrait of Benjamin with hat, Green wraps, thick border, flag and eagle printed in one color (Box 2)
    - Das kleine Buch (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, ca. 1907 ) 48 p., 2 copies (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: 1st edition. Allen notes copy with red wraps as later issue, ca. 1908.)
    - Das kleine Buch (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, ca. 1910 ) 48 p. (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: 2nd edition. Pale green wraps.)
    - A late brief explanation of time ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, ca. 1905 ]) 32 p., 2 copies 1 original (damaged); 1 photocopy (complete) (Box 2)
    - Letter of Pontius Pilate to Caesar, the sovereign at Rome. Recorded at Rome, Italy ([Los Angeles, Calif.: Anthony P. King, ca. 1910 ]) 8 p., 2 copies (Box 2)
      (Allen annotation: Originally published by Anthony P. King of Los Angeles, a few copies were secured by the colony and new wraps printed and circulated among the members. A House of David edition was issued much later.)
    - Letter of Pontius Pilate to Caesar, the sovereign at Rome. Recorded at Rome, Italy (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, [ 1974 ]) 8 p. (Box 2)
    - Den lilla boken: i ängelns hand (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, [ca. 1925 ] 34 p. (Box 3)
      (Allen annotation: Swedish translation of "The little book" translated by a member of the colony. The date of publication was secured from a member of the colony who recalled the circumstances of its printing.)
    - The little book: in the hand of the angel. Rev. 10:2. The hand was sent unto me, and lo! a roll of a book was therein. ... Addressed to the twelve tribes of Israel scattered abroad, greeting (Benton Harbor, Mich.: [Israelite House of David, ca. 1903 ]) 32 p. (Box 3)
      (Allen annotation: 1st edition. In some copies of the first edition an appended leaf is bound in notifying of the establishment of a "Headquarters for the ingathering of Israel in Australia." These copies would be issued 1905 and after.)
    - The little book: in the hand of the angel. Rev. 10:2. The hand was sent unto me, and lo! a roll of a book was therein. ... Addressed to the twelve tribes of Israel scattered abroad, greeting (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, [ca. 1906 ]) 36 p. (Box 3)
      (Allen annotation: 2nd edition. Reset and revised and enlarged to 36 p. The notice of the Australian headquarters now appears printed on the inside upper wrap. The wrapper title is within a double ruled border. The trumpet insignia is of a simpler design than used on the first edition.)
    - The little book: in the hand of the angel. Rev. 10:2. The hand was sent unto me, and lo! a roll of a book was therein. ... Addressed to the twelve tribes of Israel scattered abroad, greeting (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, [ca. 1910 ]) 36 p. (Box 3)
      (Allen annotation: 3rd edition again revised with considerable textual variation. This edition was used for several years without change. It is quite probable that a quantity was printed and then bound up as needed. There is a running title in this edition. Cover title within double ruled border and still a different cut of the trumpet insignia is used.)
    - The little book: in the hand of the angel. Rev. 10:2. The hand was sent unto me, and lo! a roll of a book was therein. ... Addressed to the twelve tribes of Israel scattered abroad, greeting (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, [ca. 1915 ]) 32 p. (Box 3)
      (Allen annotation: 4th edition. Revised and shortened to 32 p. Some copies have a frontis portrait of Benjamin. The format is noticeably smaller.)
    - The little book: in the hand of the angel. Rev. 10:2. ... Addressed to the twelve tribes of Israel scattered abroad, greeting (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, [ 19-- ]) 32 p. [Later printings], 6 copies (Box 3)
    - Little book of life see Book of life (Box 3)
    - The new House of David: the bridal church of the first born son of God (Benton Harbor, Mich.: [Israelite House of David 1903 ]) 24 p. (Box 3)
      (BHL copy accompanied by printed mailing envelope.)
      (Allen annotation: Singleton leaves printed on one side only. Signed at end "Mary and Benjamin 144 Euclid St. Benton Harbor." Without doubt the second item printed at the colony, the first being the Star.)
    - The new House of David: the bridal church of the first born son of God (Benton Harbor, Mich.: [Israelite House of David 1904 ]) 23 p. (Box 3)
      (Allen annotation: 2nd edition with revisions in the text.)
    - An open letter to all members of the House of David, Benton Harbor, Mich., October 4, 1929 (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David 1929 ) 7 p. (Box 3)
      (Allen annotation: Signed at the end by Ada (Ross) and Edith (Bell).)
    - Park rule book, 1920 ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David 1920 ]) 13 p. (Box 3)
    - Patriotic songs / by Benjamin, House of David (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, c 1918 ) 11 p., 2 copies (Box 3)
    - Poetry by Benjamin ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1916 ]) 16 p. (Box 3)
      (Allen annotation: Caption title.)
    - Poetry by Benjamin (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1917 ) 56 p., 2 copies (Box 3)
      (Allen annotation: Wrapper title: Glad tidings of great joy, peace on Earth goodwill to men. Printed in green ink.)
    - Poetry by Benjamin. Book 2 (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1917 ) 44 p., 3 copies (Box 3)
      (Allen annotation: 1st edition printed on pulp paper and without the frontis portrait. Wrapper title "Laws of creation, parting of two worlds." As with the first book of poetry this is printed in green ink.)
    - Poetry by Benjamin. Book 2 (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1917 ) 44 p. (Box 3)
      (Allen annotation: Wrapper title: Laws of creation, parting of two worlds. As with the first book of poetry this is printed in a green ink. Second edition printed on better quality paper and with frontis portrait of Benjamin.)
    - [Preacher's concordance and references book] ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, 190-]) 19 p., Photocopy. (Box 3)
      (Allen annotation: Completely without imprint or title. First leaf was written by Benjamin although the sermons in the second section May be by Mary. The title has been supplied as a descriptive measure.)
    - [Preacher's reference book] ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, ca. 1910 ]) 64 p. (Box 3)
      (Allen annotation: Without title or imprint.)
    - Preacher's reference book (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, ca. 1910 ) 22 p. (Box 3)
    - Prince of Peace and King of Glory: a descriptive account of the birth, crucifixion, resurrection and ascension of Jesus (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1913 ) 67 p. (Box 3)
      (Allen annotation: Some copies have printed cancels posted in over portions of the text. Curiously enough some of these cancels have been in turn canceled.)
    - Prince of Peace and King of Glory ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1913 ]) 67 p. (Box 3)
      (Allen annotation: The text is as in the regular edition prior to the cancels. There is no imprint or printing information and no publication list. These copies were for the use of the cast only.)
    - Prince of Peace, King of Glory: the ministry, crucifixion and resurrection of Jesus ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, ca. 1904 ]) 48 p., 2 copies (Box 3)